Finding Aid for Washtenaw County Community Mental Health Center. Substance Abuse Coordinating Agency Records, 1970-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Agencies and Programs 1971-1988
  - Child and Family Services 1971-1986
    - Drug Treatment Program (DTP) 1983-1986, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - General Information 1971-1982 (scattered) (Box 11)
    - Licensing
      - Livingston County-Howell 1975-1978, 1980 (Box 11)
      - Pittsfield 1984, 1986 (Box 11)
      - Ypsilanti 1983-1984 (Box 11)
    - Program Review/Record Audit 1975-1976 (Box 11)
  - Child Care Coordinating and Referral Service 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Clinical Resources, Inc. 1983 (Box 11)
  - Community Center Project 1974, 1976 (Box 11)
  - Community Education and Information, undated 1973-1974 (Box 11)
  - Community Mental Health Treatment Facility 1979-1982
    - Contracts and Budgets 1979-1982 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Quarterly On-Site Reviews 1980-1981 (Box 11)
  - Community Re-entry Program 1976-1977 (Box 12)
  - Consultation and Learning Center, Inc. 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Dawn Farm, Inc. 1978-1986
    - Contracts and Budgets 1978-1983 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1978-1985, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - General Information 1979-1983 (Box 12)
    - Licensing 1983-1984, 1986, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Dawntreader, Inc. 1979 (Box 12)
  - Drug Help 1972-1981
    - Contracts and Budgets 1972-1973, 1977-1980 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1978-1981 (Box 12)
    - General Information 1973-1974, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - Licensing 1974, 1978-1980 (Box 12)
    - Record Audit 1975-1977 (Box 12)
  - Employee Assistance Associates, Inc. 1983 (Box 12)
  - Family Therapy Project-University of Michigan 1979-1981 (Box 12)
  - 15th District Court 1974-1984 (scattered) (Box 12)
  - 53rd District Court 1983, 1985 (Box 12)
  - 14th District Court 1983, 1985-1986 (Box 12)
  - Huron Valley Institute 1979-1982 (Box 12)
  - Intervention Associates 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Livingston Co. Community Mental Health Services 1973, 1976-1983
    - Contracts and Budgets 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence 1979-1982 (Box 12)
    - General Information 1979-1981 (Box 12)
    - Licensing 1980-1983 (Box 12)
    - Livingston County Mental Health Plan 1973 (Box 12)
  - Livingston County Crisis Center 1976-1979
    - Contracts and Budgets 1977-1979 (Box 12)
    - Licensing 1976-1979 (Box 12)
  - Maxey Training School Report 1988 (Box 13)
  - McPherson Community Health Center 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Mental Health Resources Center 1984 (Box 13)
  - Mercywood Hospital 1981-1986, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Michigan Clearinghouse for Substance Abuse Information, undated 1981-1982 (Box 13)
  - Michigan Deaconess Treatment Services 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Minister's Alliance of Ypsilanti, Ann Arbor and Vicinity 1983 (Box 13)
  - Octagon House 1973-1982
    - Contracts and Budgets 1974-1979 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence 1973-1975, 1977-1982, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - General Information, undated 1973-1979 (scattered) (Box 13)
    - Program Audit/Record Review 1973-1979 (Box 13)
    - Transition Committee 1974-1975 (Box 13)
  - Operation Get-It-Together Community Drug Crisis Center 1973-1976 (Box 13)
  - Ozone House 1974-1976 (Box 13)
  - Project Trans-Action-Howell High School 1976 (Box 13)
  - Saline Community Hospital-Substance Abuse Program 1979-1985
    - General Information 1979-1982 (Box 14)
    - Licensing 1977-1985, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - SHAR House-Huron Valley 1979-1980 (Box 14)
  - Share House 1974-1988
    - Contracts and Budgets 1975-1983 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1979-1985, 1988 (Box 14)
    - General Information, undated 1974-1982 (scattered) (Box 14)
    - Licensing 1983-1986, 1988, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - SOS Community Crisis Center 1971-1983
    - Contracts and Budgets 1973-1980 (scattered) (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1978-1981 (Box 14)
    - General Information 1971-1980 (scattered) (Box 14)
    - Licensing 1974-1983 (scattered) (Box 14)
    - Record Audit 1975 (Box 14)
  - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital 1975-1984
    - Contracts and Budgets 1975-1980 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1976-1982 (scattered) (Box 14)
    - General Information 1975, 1979-1981 (Box 14)
    - Licensing 1974, 1976, 1979, 1981-1984, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Program Review on Substance Abuse 1979 (Box 14)
  - University of Michigan Alcoholism and Other Chemical Dependencies Clinic 1974-1984
    - Contracts and Budgets 1974-1980 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1978-1981 (Box 14)
    - General Information, undated 1975, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - Licensing 1974, 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Washtenaw Community Services, Inc. 1977-1978 (Box 15)
  - Washtenaw Council on Alcoholism 1971, 1974-1984
    - Annual Reports 1977, 1980 (Box 15)
    - Contracts and Budgets 1974-1984 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence 1974-1984, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - General Information, undated 1974-1984 (Box 15)
    - Grant Applications 1971, 1980 (Box 15)
    - Guides to Alcoholism Resources 1974, 1978 (Box 15)
    - Licensing 1983 (Box 15)
    - Minutes 1976-1983 (scattered) (Box 15)
    - Proposals 1975, 1976, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Washtenaw County Alcohol Highway Safety Education Program 1975-1976, 1983-1986
    - Contracts and Budgets 1975-1976 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence 1975-1976, 1985 (Box 15)
    - Licensing 1983-1986, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Wayne County Alcohol Highway Safety Education 1983 (Box 15)
  - Wayne County Substance Abuse Services 1981 (Box 15)
  - Women's Resource Center 1979-1984
    - Contracts and Budgets 1980-1984 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence 1979-1984, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Licensing 1983-1984 (Box 15)
  - Ypsilanti Resource Center 1980-1985
    - Contracts and Budgets 1980-1983 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence 1980-1984 (Box 15)
    - General Information 1980-1982, 1984 (Box 15)
    - Licensing 1984-1985 (Box 15)
- Professional and Citizens Advocacy Groups 1970, 1973-1988
  The Professional and Citizen Advocacy Groups series (1.25 linear feet) contains materials which date from 1970 to 1988, and consists of reports, minutes, resource directories, bylaws, correspondence, manuals, proposals and newsletters. The records are arranged alphabetically by name of group. They document the concerns and activities of a variety of state, local and, to a lesser degree, national organizations, which do not have an official role in the substance abuse hierarchy of the state of Michigan.
  - Citizens Blue Ribbon Committee for the Study of Drug Abuse 1970 (draft of final report) (Box 16)
  - Citizens Community Service Resource Committee-Michigan State Police-Ypsilanti Post 1976 (Box 16)
  - Citizens for Substance Abuse Services 1980 (Box 16)
  - Community Action on Substance Abuse 1981-1982 (Box 16)
  - Comprehensive Health Planning Council of Southeastern Michigan 1975-1983 (Box 16)
  - Inter-Agency Resources Committee for Washtenaw County undated (Box 16)
  - International Association of Prevention Programs 1977 (bylaws) (Box 16)
  - Livingston County Students Advocacy Consortium 1987 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Alcohol and Addiction Association 1978-1983 (scattered) (Box 16)
  - Michigan Association of Substance Abuse Coordinators, Inc. (MASAC) 1976, 1978-1988
    The Michigan Association of Substance Abuse Coordinators, Inc. (MASAC) constitutes the most significant and comprehensive records of this series. MASAC was established in 1975 as a professional association representing state-funded substance abuse program delivery coordinators from all counties in Michigan. The goal of the organization is to bring regional agency directors together in order to better provide consistent and effective substance abuse prevention, casefinding, treatment, and data collection services. The organization became a registered lobbyist in 1984 and has had substantial impact on the legislative process by interpreting substance abuse needs to the governor, the legislature and OSAS. MASAC also disseminates information on state policies and professional standards to its membership.
    - Annual Reports 1984-1986 (Box 16)
    - Bylaws, undated 1988 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1976, 1978-1988, 7 folders (Box 16)
    - Executive Committee Meetings 1980-1982, 1985 (minutes) (Box 16)
    - Fall Retreats 1982, 1984 (Box 16)
    - Financial Procedures Manual undated (Box 16)
    - General Membership Meetings 1978, 1980-1988 (minutes), 5 folders (Box 16)
    - Legislative Breakfast 1985 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous Committee minutes 1980-1982, 1985 (scattered) (Box 16)
    - Papers 1982, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Proposals 1982, 1984-1985, 1987 (Box 16)
    - Reports 1982, 1983, 1988 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Coalition on Substance Abuse 1979-1987, 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Michigan Consortium on Substance Abuse Education 1983 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Council on Alcohol Problems 1983-1985 (newsletter "MICAP RECAP") (Box 17)
  - Michigan Forum on Women and Alcohol 1980-1981 (Box 17)
  - National Council on Alcoholism 1984-1985 (Box 17)
  - National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA) 1980 (Box 17)
  - Program Director's Association 1978-1979 (Box 17)
  - Saline Area Human Services Coalition (SAHSC) 1979-1981 (Box 17)
- Topical Files 1970-1987
  The Topical Files series (0.5 linear feet) contains a diverse range of materials which cover the years 1970-1987 and consists of correspondence, bibliographies, promotional materials, reports, manuals, statistics and newsletters. These documents are generally of a background or referential nature which do not directly pertain to administrative functions of the agency.
  - Ann Arbor Public Schools 1970-1971, 1977, 1980 (Box 17)
  - Bibliographies, undated 1973 (Box 17)
  - Community Resources, undated 1972 (Box 17)
  - Conferences/Workshops 1977-1986 (scattered) (Box 17)
  - Drunk Driving Client Admissions 10/01/1983-09/30/1984, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Drunk Driving Information 1983-1984 (Box 17)
  - Elderly 1978-1983 (scattered) (Box 17)
  - Emergency Services Procedure Manual 1975 (Box 17)
  - Indians 1979 (Box 17)
  - Methadone Treatment, undated 1970, 1974-1975, 1983 (Box 17)
  - Methaqualone Information 1972 (Box 17)
  - Mortality Rates-Michigan by County 1982 (Box 17)
  - Newsletters (assorted) 1978-1987 (scattered) (Box 17)
  - Papers 1970, 1972, 1974, 1977-1979
    - "Alcohol and Sex" undated (Washtenaw Community College basic alcoholism class) (Box 17)
    - "A Case for Primary Prevention in Alcohol and Highway Safety: Where We Are and Where We Need to Go" 1974 (Box 17)
    - "Drug Use and Lifestyles of American Youth (Monitoring the Future)" 1978 (grant application) (Box 17)
    - Drugs in the Detroit/Wayne County Area 1982-1983 (reports) (Box 17)
    - "Preventing Adolescent Alcohol Misuse Through an Elementary School Based Peer Prevention Program" 1986 (Box 17)
    - "Quality Circles in the Classroom" 1988 (Box 17)
    - Michigan Innovative Drug Programs 1972, 1974 (Box 17)
    - "Unilateral Family Therapy for Alcohol Abuse" 1979 (grant application) (Box 17)
    - "Violent Crime: Potential Areas of Impact for the Area of Substance Abuse Services" 1982 (Box 17)
    - "Why the Young Use Drugs" 1970 (Box 17)
  - Paraquat Test 1978 (Box 17)
  - The Chemical People 1983-1986 (Box 17)
  - WIQB/WNRS proposal 1988 (Box 17)